welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
so check-ins my little cat Socrates is
making some noise right now and I always
view it as an opportunity to be in right
relationship with him
maybe that is a spiritual practice so
just wouldn't immune
don't turn yourself off mute so welcome
to the the stoah i am peter limber the
stewart of the stoah and this is a place
for us to cohere and dialogue about what
matters most at the nice edge of this
moment and today we have Greg Sadler and
Greg is going to deliver a talk on
staying inside on solitude and
cultivating interior life Greg's a
practical philosopher he's the editor of
the stoicism today blog he's a really
cool guy I like him it's a good energy
about him and then the last talk was
quite fun and so how it's gonna work
he's gonna show his ideas and then we're
gonna I'm gonna warm up with some
questions and then ask you a just write
down your questions in the chat box and
then I meet yourself to ask it that
being said I will allow great to unmute
himself and hand over to you alright
well thanks for inviting me back in much
enjoyed our last session as well and so
yeah the topic is staying inside which
we're all supposed to be doing at this
point in time some people have more
trouble with that than than others and
we'll talk a little bit about that in in
part of the presentation and so what I'm
going to talk about is drawing on a
number of different thinkers who all
I'll mention and give references to
anybody who wants to contact me later
for follow-ups about well you know you
talked about Rilke we're looking real
good for that feel free to do that and
so what I'm going to run through most of
which is just me throwing ideas out
there at you
but the last two which will be a little
bit more interactive are the following
first I want to talk about this notion
of
your life and what it means and you know
why we would turn to philosophy to
understand it and then we'll talk about
why why it's good for us to cultivate
interior life when it sounds like yet
one more thing that we were supposed to
be doing and then I'll talk about the
the crisis that we're in and the
opportunities that were given and some
of the challenges as well then I also
want to explore something that's really
connected with this this notion of
solitude so you see that in the title
well what is that well we'll go into
that and I'll be bringing in some stoic
thinkers and some existentialist
thinkers to talk about that another
closely related topic is something that
we start to work on if we look at
ourselves and we find that we're not
entirely happy with it which is this
goal of integrating the self and and it
ties in well with you know what Peter
was referencing in spiritual practices a
lot of those spiritual practices from
antiquity on are aimed at that an idea
then solitude and integrating the self
fit in with each other then I'll I'll
consider an issue that I think is almost
it automatically arises you know there's
worry about well if I'm if I'm
retreating into myself then aren't I
cutting off my relationships with others
and that's a valid concern but one that
turns out to be unnecessary if we're
doing it right and then we'll talk about
some obstacles to cultivating solitude
and and a rich interior life and that's
where we'll get a little bit more
interactive I've got a few that I want
to bring up but I'm sure that some of
you do as well and then I'll talk about
some recommendations that I have and I'm
not I'm not coming up with anything new
this is all just coming from these
authors who I'm referencing but we might
come up with some some other good
practices for supporting and maintaining
solitude so interior life this is a kind
of a technical term in and some
you could call them traditions of
spiritual developments there's a lot of
other synonyms for this we can talk
about the inner world of one's own
person interior already gets used a lot
Stoics like to use this concept of the
inner citadel which comes from Marcus
Aurelius if you actually look at
epictetus he says watch out for inner
Citadel's because that's where not all
of them are great that's that's
sometimes what the vise is set up within
us with Rilke we have this space of
solitude or Hinds ohm kite that we're
going to talk about in a bit you know
and it's made its way into popular
culture I remember in the Sherlock
Holmes show that that BBC put out in the
last five years or so he talked about
retreating to his interior castle or
inner castle or mind castle it's how he
framed it right and all of these are
really touching on the same idea all of
us have the beginnings of this just by
being human beings it's part of normal
human development if you didn't have
some sort of interior already that's
that's you on your own you really
wouldn't be able to function well and
it's been a major topic of focus in many
of the ancient traditions of virtue
ethics so we can think about Platonism
aristotelianism stoicism as being the
heavy hitters in that respect but it's
also something that the existentialist
gave a lot of attention to various other
you know wisdom traditions whether
philosophical or they just have have
spent a lot of time on discussing this
and some forms of psychotherapy as well
now some psychological perspectives
would rule this out if any of you
remember behaviorism which is kind of a
dead thing at this time you know there's
no interior already at all well it turns
out that was that was quite false many
many other forms of psychotherapy and
psychology have you know viewed this as
something quite important so it's it's
it's a you could say it's a concept that
corresponds to an experience but it's
not a simple one it's something that's
complex and it's a little bit you know
funny that we can talk about it in the
general because if we're talking about
it correctly there it exists in you and
you and you and me and it exists in a
sort of independent though similar way
in all of us so there's some interesting
problems that get raised by that which
we can talk about a little bit later on
but the point is we can we can
understand it and we can develop it and
we can use it because it is not just a
part of us
it is us this is us understanding
ourselves in the depth of our being so
why do we need to develop interior life
and not just interior life but interior
life of a certain kind I wanted to begin
with with Blaise Pascal's dictum he says
that and there's a little bit over
playing his hand here but but it's quite
true in many respects humanities
problems stem from human beings
inability to sit quietly in a room alone
I think you've all heard that before and
it's quite true you know people seek out
distractions oftentimes seek out
conflicts and they do so in ways that
sometimes are not particularly good for
them so why do we need solitude why do
we need an interior life it helps us to
develop a kind of independence and
self-sufficiency that that's needed in
order to be autonomous human beings and
be able to you know sit quietly in a
room alone or a waiting room or wherever
else we're supposed to be and it also
allows us to develop a responsiveness
and attentiveness that we otherwise
might be lacking and not just to what's
going on within ourselves but also
what's happening with with other people
to be able to take note of when somebody
else is struggling and say the the thing
that could be helpful at that point in
time or to be able to share in the joys
or sorrows of another and so you know it
sounds kind of paradoxical in that
you're withdrawing from things but
you're withdrawing so that you can come
back to them we also I think need this
and you know the again this will sound a
little counterintuitive we're all stuck
at home so you can take a break whenever
you want to right you can sleep in if
you'd like to there are the essential
people have to go off to work but many
of us are doing work from home or were
just staying at home well you can wear
yourself out even even on a vacation and
so what we're talking about is solitude
here is needed for sort of recharging
and reconnecting to deeper and more
important things getting away from the
superficial aspects of life and into the
deeper aspects of life and this leads us
to be able to engage in self-discovery
in a variety of different ways and and
not the sort of navel-gazing
narcissistic self-discovery that they
would then announce itself on social
media to everybody Hey look what I found
in my solitude or something like that
but so you know being able to honestly
assess who we are and get to know
ourselves better and that includes a lot
of things that we might not be entirely
happy with I'll talk about that in a bit
but this is necessary
Rilke is probably the person who has
identified this that the best it's
necessary in order to generate a kind of
depth within ourselves and the lack of
that depth is part of why Pascal is
right about about many people or even
about those who are developing it but
aren't using it at the right time and so
if we're if we're cultivating this it
can lead to better relationships with
others and to the world as a whole or to
other things we might think about nature
we might think about you know animals or
all sorts of other things that were in
relation to and now we're presented with
some some very interesting opportunities
and challenges in the present one of
these of course is staying inside you
know because of the pandemic those of us
who are actually
following stay-at-home orders
understandably there there are some of
our states here in America where the
governor's haven't actually declared
stay-at-home workers unfortunately but
you know the ones that that are on track
have told us all to stay inside and when
we're outside
we're isolated from each other we're
engaging in social distancing we're
supposed to be wearing masks
which already hide a good portion of our
face that we would use to understand
what's going on with other key people
from each other yeah I remember when I
first started walking our dog with a
mask she was kind of upset about it she
didn't she didn't like the fact that she
couldn't see what was going on on the
but in my eyes and I think there's a lot
of that with people so there's there's a
lot of isolation going on and some
people look at this with a kind of
hostility you know who are you to
interrupt my activities and tell me I
can't be next to people and do whatever
I want to do there's other you know
we're seeing some interesting protests
going on right now a lot of which I
think are driven by ideological you know
ideological judgments on their parts
some people are very driven by fear for
their own self but I think this offers
us an opportunity to look at the things
that we're supposed to be doing in terms
of justice towards other people we don't
want to get other people sick and a kind
of decency and that's that's one topic
and we could explore that more but then
what do we do we're even if we have the
right sort of mindset were stuck in
these constrained spaces unless you're a
celebrity I don't know if any of you saw
the celebrity video with all of them in
their palatial homes singing imagine
they have got a lot of backlash from
that because people are like man I'm
stuck in my studio apartment look at
these people
so if you're if you're not a celebrity
and you're stuck in something but
smaller you might you might have a sense
of being stir-crazy or isolated and
we're also stuck with other people you
know interesting some some other the
people have been like talking about
being stuck
with their ex in the same apartment so
that you know you don't have a choice
about who you're spending time with and
you know even your pets might might get
out of your nerves from time to time you
know there's this funny thing that I
think some of you may have seen where
you know that all the dogs are saying
you know quarantine should go on forever
and the cats are saying everyone needs
to get back to the work my experience
has not been that with my cat who has
been very attention-seeking sometimes to
the point where she'll interrupt the
video work things like that so you know
we've got all these things going on but
you know we also have the opportunity at
this point in time to to develop
something that maybe some of us have
done but we haven't done to the degree
that we'd like and that would include
myself and we have this opportunity to
learn from from ancient and medieval and
modern thinkers about the resources for
developing a rich interior life so I
want to talk about this conception of
solitude in German it's a Nizam kite
that's the word that that Rilke and
Nietzsche use and in Greek it's animals
that's the word that Epictetus use is
that's the word by the way that we get
hermit from a hermit is somebody who
goes off into maybe the desert or the
wasteland to be alone and so so it has
to do with this being alone and there's
good and bad valence --is to these ideas
it can also be translated as loneliness
and even in Rilke Rilke has two
different poems that are that are
referencing eye exam one of them is
about these two lovers that can't get
along with each other and having laying
in bed with back-to-back with each other
and they are totally alone even though
they're in the same room with each other
and the way it's translated in the lobe
I think is the old father translation of
epictetus is forlorn this which is a
nice English term and epictetus devotes
some some attention to it so you know
what makes this bad for other people
what are we experiencing that that's
negative right now part of it could be
disconnection from others and that's
when we want
actions with others and we can't happen
so you know for example I get with my
children who live two states away by
phone and text and you know that that
sort of thing it would be nice to be in
the same room with them at the same time
I haven't seen them since Christmas time
and who knows how long the quarantines
right but you know we're still able to
maintain some connection I think there's
a lot of people who just are
disconnected entirely from those who
they would want to be connected with
another thing that epictetus picks out
he says what is it that people don't
like about being on their own that makes
them feel that it's a negative
experience and he talks about the
perception that you're without resources
that you don't have what you need to to
deal with things to cope with things and
I think that's that's a common thing is
but you know worries of that well what
if something happens to me who's going
to take care of me and then another
thing that that could be the case for
those who are in you know quarantine
with others but are still experiencing
the negative side of items on kite or
solitude would be not being able to be
understood by others being sort of cut
off from not being recognized or
acknowledged in the way that say you
know Hagel talks about in the
phenomenology where that's that's really
the central thing driving that at work
by the way is drive for recognition from
other people for being acknowledged and
those are the negative sides of it there
are some very positive sides to solitude
as well and epictetus talks about this
in in a chapter in his discourses and
he's kind of representative of an
ancient view on solitude it's important
to be able to be on one's own that is a
goal for a fully developed human being
and he uses Zeus being and of course we
don't we don't believe all this but some
of the Stoics believe there was a world
conflagration at the end of this
universe though the whole place had
burned off and all that's left is
and Epicurus why me Azusa and lonely and
whining by himself when that happens no
he's he's a okay why because he can
stand to be by himself because he's
friends with himself he has a friend who
believe relation with himself Aristotle
says without all the metaphysics a very
similar thing in his discussions of
friendship can a person be friends with
themselves and that's that's that's an
important insight there Marcus Aurelius
of course has this metaphor of the inner
Citadel that I think many of us like the
most important thing about the inner
Citadel thing is thinking about what do
you actually do in there what's in that
inner Citadel is it just a place to you
know withdraw and retreat and keep the
world at bay which is what the metaphor
would seem to imply or are you
cultivating something inside of there
you know I guess it would depend on how
big your castle walls are you know what
you're able to put in there
Christian thinkers particularly monastic
writers like John Cassian view the the
you know withdraw to oneself as a place
where you can really see yourself as
what you are apart from the social self
that you share with everybody else and
encounter the divine and carry out a
process of healing or transformation you
see this by the way in st. Anselm's
prosto gym which is essentially a prayer
rather than a work of you know strict
argumentation i'm the existentialist
they grasp that it's important to be
able to build meaning on your own that
is not being given to you by just
cultural constructs or processes and so
you see Nietzsche talking about the need
for solitude it's less folks are through
straw but notice it's not just a
solitude of withdrawing entirely by
oneself
it's a solitude that you can share with
another solitary for nature and Rilke
would say something quite similar with
with Rainer Maria Rilke I would say this
concept of solitude particularly in
letters to a young poet but also in some
of his other works is developed to the
greatest degree and he talks about at
the very first this you know letter to
this young man he said
drawn to yourself and enter into the
space of solitude where you can identify
what your real desires are and see
whether you need to write whether you
need to be a poet if not do something
else and if you can't think of topics to
write enter into your solitude and think
about your childhood now he's telling
him to think about his childhood because
the man is a young man we can say think
about your other memories you know I'm
nearly 50 so I can think about you know
what was going on with one of our dogs
that we've lost and the memories of him
from just a few years ago but enter into
yourself
Andrea propriate those and you'll you'll
always have material to work on and and
we'll go suggest this not just for the
you know the purpose of creativity but
to get to know who you are and so one of
the other key ideas with this is this
notion of integration of oneself
integration of who you are what do we
find when we go inside this is one
reason a lot of people don't want to go
inside we find that we're a mess I mean
you know virtue ethics is not about
telling us the perfect blueprint for how
we ought to be and then we just snap to
it and you know impose that upon
ourselves what we find out whether we're
taking a university liyan path or a
stoical path or an existentialist path
or some sort of monastic Christian path
is that we are a battleground of
different ideas and desires and
assumptions and they war with each other
Epictetus actually uses this this term
that gets translated as contradiction
it's really Maki it means conflict it
means fighting and this the you know the
goal is to become less like that and why
you know because it makes us happier to
be like that and so when we're talking
about integrating ourself we have this
experience over and over again of only
partial integration and a conflict we
might even realize that we're in some
respects bad people and then we're posed
with the question well do I just simply
embrace that and say I'm a person
forever
or deny it and repress it and project it
out on to others or do we say wow I've
got stuff to work on I better like pay
more attention to this entering into
solitude being by oneself offers
possibilities for doing this provided
one uses resources that are available
rather than trying to reinvent the wheel
and we might also think about what are
we actually aiming at when we're talking
about integrating the self are we
looking at this higher kind of self that
you know we've got you know think about
plato's try parts on tripartite so if
you've got reason dictating everything
down to everybody else and they have to
fall in line that's not even like a good
read of Plato by the way but that is a
common portrayal of it or is it rather
than we want to allow the different
parts of ourselves to communicate with
each other to make their cases to each
other and to have their legitimate
places but also limitations placed on
each other this is what what
Rilke suggests we would be able to do
and this is what epictetus suggests we
would be able to do through engaging in
a bit of analysis and that you know
presupposes that we make the space from
that analysis ideally for Rilke if any
of you haven't read the letters to a
young poet what you see him talking
about is the discovery of his self and
the the the development of his self who
isn't just by itself but within that
space finds sort of organic connections
with with nature with God with plants
and animals other people places
experiences and even metaphysical things
here the things he calls the big things
like fate and death and so you know he
actually we can talk about a metaphysics
of solitude he says we all belong to one
vast solitude sort of like when we go
down we find some common roots or
bedrock that we all share with it now I
noticed I'm taking up quite a bit of
time go through this a little bit
quicker one main concern I think a lot
of people would have in hearing this is
okay well this sounds really great I go
into myself
and I cultivate this space of solitude
and okay I've got these thinkers that
can help me out with that but isn't that
going to isolate me more from other
people in my life and the answer would
be well if you're doing it wrong yes if
you're I mean let's say you're you're
being a jerk to everybody so they won't
bother you and you know they can't
intrude into your private time or
something like that
you punish them for that that's gonna
screw things up but ideally becoming
solitary in this way self-sufficient
spontaneous more able to know who you
are should allow you to have more
genuine relationships with others which
is dependent on them of course you know
if you can't have a really great genuine
relationship with somebody who is a
terrible person but you know I think in
a lot of cases we often get in our own
way in our relationships with people who
aren't terrible persons and we can have
good relationships with them and Rilke
again has a really wonderful way of
framing this in I believe it's letter
seven he when he's talking about love
and how it fits in with solitude and the
need for developing ourselves before
love commit ourselves to others you know
in loving relationships he says that
that love is at its highest two
solitudes that protect and border and
greet each other so the idea would be
that love is not a fusion where you lose
yourself and the other person or
anything like that it's two people who
can actually be on their own but choose
to be with each other somebody else who
talks about this by the way similar way
Lizzie Marcus Tullius Cicero in his on
friendship he talks about you know his
friendship or her loving relationships
are these based on just needing
something from the other are finding our
missing part or something like that he
says there are a lot of
people who don't need anything from
somebody else is his example of this is
Scipio africanus and they overflow they
give to others in friendship because
they see that as a good thing and so I
think building ourselves developing
ourselves within this space of Solitude
can very well equip us for doing the
things you need to do for others
particularly in this crisis you know
many of us have others who are dependent
on us psychologically financially in
other ways in the case of my students
for getting their grades in on time and
getting guidance and so by by being able
to build ourselves up and understand
ourselves better and pare away at the
parts of ourselves that we want to to
fix and improve in this space of
Solitude we can actually be more
available and accessible to others so
obstacles here's where I think we could
take you know a bit of back and forth
discussion I think one of the biggest
obstacles is distraction and I think
social media can be a big part of that
people are spending a lot more time
online and getting in fights on Twitter
I know this just looking at my own
Twitter stream I've done a lot of muting
of people myself so that I don't have to
like watch the endless bickering the
other things we might think about people
who are spending an awful lot of time
gaming or consuming streaming content
there's nothing inherently bad about
those things as a matter of fact you
there might be ways to connect with
other people but they can also be ways
in which we lose ourselves when we try
to you know consume the time that we
could otherwise be spending on this
another thing that I think and I've seen
this coming from social media is this
this demand that's coming from some
people that we all be super productive I
think some of you have seen the memes
where people are saying things like
if you haven't learned a language or
started a business or done this or that
during quarantine you lack
self-discipline and you know basically
the point is you're a loser right and
these are very counterproductive as a
matter of fact it doesn't even have to
go to those sort of toxic memes I have
students who say you know I'm seeing
other students posting in the discussion
forums and I just don't feel like doing
it and I feel like like I'm a failure
for not doing it I you know I did a
video to tell my students whatever good
you do that's that's something you know
don't don't downplay it don't measure
yourself against others I think that
that's sort of an enemy to the kind of
solitude that we're talking about where
you you take if not necessarily just
yourself as the measure you take you
know classic spiritual directors or
thinkers or things like that as a
potential measure I know for me another
big obstacle is not being able to go out
in nature very easily I get to go
outside three times a day to walk our
dog and we do have a little park across
the street but I live in downtown
Milwaukee and we have a lot of green
space here in Milwaukee because of our
socialist mayor's past but I can't at
this point in time go and enjoy it oh I
I would you know normally be spending
quite a lot of time outside and I think
this may be the case for many of you as
well so then we have to focus on the
things that we can do you know maybe I
spend more time hanging out with my cat
who is a part of nature noticing just
how many fuzzy she is in comparison to
the dark you know or we can talk about
other things I can I we have a nice
window fortunately so I can I can open
it and get a breeze I can watch the
birds fly our home and another obstacle
I think would be other people in our
households particularly if they're
especially you know attention-seeking of
their meeting needy that might make it
difficult to cultivate solitude so what
if Peters amenable to this what are some
of the obstacles that year
are facing besides those want to open it
up to the room for that yeah and then
I'll talk about some suggestions and
then other people can get suggestions
too sure yeah I feel like this group has
discernment so feel free just to unmute
yourself and then you can say
I'm Greg how does this play out if
you're an introvert versus an extrovert
during these times why don't I take that
sort of question afterwards okay in the
Q&A I'm looking for any sort of other
obstacles that people are having one
obstacle could possibly be broken up
sleep times I'm trying I'm you running a
set of procedures kind of like stop what
am i doing right now
there are three possible things I could
be doing right now studying philosophy I
could be exercising or I could be
meditating those are like the three
things right the meditation is the one
that's the weakest so as I'm watching
youtube videos of philosophy lectures it
turns into I don't know what that cliche
or trope cats playing piano 'he's right
so then watching that for a while as a
refreshment I suddenly realize hey wait
a minute I'm spending too much time on
this right so that's two things the the
breaking up of sleep I'm not sleeping as
regularly as I could that affects my
concentration so then now I have to
manage my concentration and make sure
that I'm doing something that is of
value to me for me philosophy is of high
value so I try to put that high in the
priorities but there still are multiple
distractions so it's about concentration
and distraction for me yeah I mean the
sleep thing is definitely an issue I
know if I don't get I can operate on
like six or seven hours of sleep if I
get less than that I'm pretty much shot
for the next day but what I hear you
saying the other obstacle would be sort
of like picking between different things
which one you use you ought to be
doing and then having to prioritize
between them I wonder too if there isn't
it kind of when it comes to spiritual
practices I think all of you have heard
of FOMO fear of missing out is this
worried that well if I'm not if I'm
doing this I'm not able to do this at
the same time and I think that can also
be disabling so it's that many of us it
keeps us from being able to give
ourselves entirely to the one thing that
we are doing any other any other
challenges people are facing good yes I
this is a very brief one I have a friend
on the East Coast who is infected with
the virus and he's Ahnold like a
lockdown that is perhaps more extreme
than the rest of us we can move around
our homes we can open a window he's
really locked in one room he lives with
his daughter and but he's you know he's
quite old and he feels like he's in a
prison because he's infected he can't
even leave his room yeah that's that's a
very tough one and as a matter of fact
that reminds me I teach classes online
for prisoners here in Wisconsin and I've
only seen a few of my students recently
and see that means being able to chat
with them electronically because they're
all in lockdown now and they can't you
know they came to recharge their their
tablets that they use for their classes
and so it's real it's real isolation
yeah I think that so to say to somebody
like that oh well you've got the
opportunity to cultivate solitude almost
seems like a slap in the face right so I
don't know that this this advice is is
particularly helpful for extreme cases
like that
but let's talk about some suggestions
then so I can tell you the things that
I've found helpful for doing this and I
think many of you as I've been talking
about this you probably recognize that
you've done things you know like that as
well and that you're engaged in
in cultivating this interior space so
you might say what's been helpful for
you for me obviously drawing on other
authors who have things to say about it
that's that's always helpful for me and
exploring you know for example what
Rilke has to say about solitude in his
letters to a young poet in his poems in
his novels and then in his other letters
to other people it places me in
communication with Rilke and helps me to
sort of figure out what's going along
and I find myself quite emotionally
involved when I when I when I read and
then when I teach Rilke because I teach
them routinely to my classes there's a
there's a kind of a connection there and
there's probably people like that for
you as well I think you know maintaining
and this will mark is talking about this
a little bit - the need for
concentration this deliberate focus on
on what is really essential and meaning
you know at least for that space and
time sort of pushing other things to the
side trying to eliminate the
distractions that we have for myself as
well and maybe some of you are like this
if you're somebody who is often over
scheduled and has a lot of things on
their their to-do list every day then
when you find yourself with these these
moments where you're daydreaming or just
kind of thing following out a train of
thought or thinking about an experience
you can recognize that and instead of
like cutting a lot of trip you know it's
almost like let's not turn off the valve
you just let it flow because there
you're actually entering into this this
place of solitude the way that you know
these thinkers had conceived a bit that
may not be a challenge for many of you
maybe some of you have no problems doing
that myself I actually have to like make
a deliberate effort not to cut off that
space of Solitude the other thing that I
think is important is making time for it
maybe you pick out a particular hour of
the day mark mentioned meditation that
can be a great way to do this as well
there's a lot of different modes and
ways of doing that
other people you know what one thing
that I don't do that I think a lot of
other people find it incredibly helpful
is journaling and the only reason I
don't do journaling is because my
writing is terrible and I find it to be
a lot of effort and I don't really have
that much much time for it but I know
that a lot of people find that
incredibly helpful for getting to know
who they are and bringing things to
lights and and many of these great
thinkers who were talking about Marcus
Aurelius right he's writing a journal to
himself I don't know if any have been
reading Peters own sort of replication
of that he's doing something similar to
that in his letters so that can be quite
good it looks like we have a question in
the chat about so this ties in with the
obstacles how about the surrounding
environment yeah we make the connection
that our houses are a place of rest a
lot of study or work it makes it hard to
study in our home so two different
things going on there yeah if we've if
we've got the mindset that our houses
are a refuge a place of rest maybe we
have to do a mindset shift to make them
a place of study or work and this is
probably one reason why it's been
difficult for many people to transition
to working from home for me I've been
working from home you know as a teacher
my entire time you do so much work at
home and then you go to wherever you're
teaching but there's also another really
good point to that like we have
construction going on around us
constantly because one thing that you
can still spend money on during this
covent pandemic is construction work and
it's a good idea it keeps people
employed right the construction workers
tend to spend their money quite a bit so
and there's less people on the street so
I'm not knocking it but it does create
for a good bit of noise and distraction
from from time to time and I think there
could be similar things going around
with other people as well you know like
what if that great me you know all you
saw the Italians singing on their
balconies did any
you see the meme where somebody tried
doing that in New York and his neighbors
like opened up their windows and they're
like shut the hell up you know not
everybody likes that that that sort of
thing kind of kind of based on cultural
assumptions I'd say so let's go back to
the suggestions thing what other
suggestions do any of you have for how
to you know cultivate this this interior
space well one thing is coming up Greg
is what we were talking about before
when the people in is sort of
reconnecting with old friends and I
mentioned how I'm sort of viewing that
as a spiritual practice reconnecting
with friends in high school and
university and you kind of there's a
like a sense I get like you kind of know
which ones you need to connect with
because there's like this sense of
unfinished business there
yeah and I've connected with like three
or four people who haven't talked to in
years and we reconnected you know shared
our stories and it was beautiful so yeah
I think that like connecting with people
being in right relationship with the
people you were called to be in right
relationship with is quite an
opportunity right now yeah and again we
were talking about this a little bit
before we started and I was saying that
Peter should do some writing about this
because I think that actually is a
legitimate spiritual practice it's got
some sort of structured procedures to it
you might say there's some definite ends
there's probably ways to do it not to do
it so I think I think that's actually a
good suggestion Maria has do you want to
read what Maria answered do you want me
to do it Maria if you want to unmute
yourself and share your thought this is
quite a good one actually marina sorry
I'm sorry yeah yeah I'll unmute you
yeah I yes I'm not marina this is my
work account that's mark yeah my name is
mark right okay I have been doing this I
don't know how successful it is but I'm
waking up in the more
instead of leaping out of bed and
rushing to get into the car in order to
make it to work on time I'm laying in
bed and it's not sleeping it's not
dreaming I'm awake but I can imagine and
remember because I have lots of time and
what I've been trying to do is remember
key points in my life there are times in
my life when my memories are very not
quite vivid but the fact that I can
remember them now tells me that they
were vivid at the time right I'm always
concerned about memory do I remember the
original event or do I remember the last
time I remembered it right we got a copy
theory perhaps in there that after what
jumped but regardless of that I'm
looking at past times that I can
actually remember in the first person
and I'm wondering why do I remember
these I'm also trying to link them
sequentially after trying to put them in
a rough order remember this is so vague
I question how well I'm doing this then
I'm looking back at that time and then
trying to see why am i what am I
remembering why do I remember this
what's the importance of that was I part
of it it was you know was I too hard on
myself did I expect too much of myself
when you're younger you kind of have an
idea of maybe the goal of the kind of
person you'd want to be right how does
that happen
how far did I go along the road you know
that sort of thing so on one hand
there's the first-person memory at that
time on the second hand there's the that
first-person memory of me now
remembering it and trying to order them
then there's an attempt to understand it
and put it in context right I won't go
into too long because if I went I could
this could hours and who wants to listen
to that right but you know like being 8
years old and expecting that I should
work and take care of myself was
somewhat unreasonable ok yeah I think
that that's the sort of thing that Rilke
is is referencing what he's talking
about you know going back into your past
and he talks about is this like vast
treasure that that we have and then you
know you engage you sort of like you
connect up with the the previous you who
you know is you but of course a very
different person than you are now you
know the one thing the one thing for me
it's like I'm constantly trying to
recontextualize because when I was a kid
I had no real understanding of the world
around me
yeah providing a frame of reference yes
right so what I wind up doing is I wind
up going back to the first person
experienced as a kid and then looking at
like what little history I know and try
to get like I won't use cosmic view that
sounds too grandiose or something but
like a multiple contextual view of that
would my my little experience would be
nested in that whether I knew it or not
yeah that's that's finding I mean we
often talk about like trying to find
meaning right and a lot of our finding
meaning is just that putting things into
a context where we can we can think that
well this is probably not all BS right
there's there's something really true
going on here this is often a very
difficult thing to articulate but you
know you see a lot of authors talking
about this including psychoanalytic
authors this this by the way is exactly
what Lacan E and analysis is about it's
not about like trying to cure somebody
or you know make them a perfect person
or anything like that it's to figure out
narratives that actually make sense put
things into perspective allow us to be
able to exercise some agency where we
need to and to be okay with the past
without calling everything great that
wasn't wasn't great let me take let me
look at its cause response how about how
about doing as Jewish people do have a
day dedicated to solitude no electron
almost necessary and no work either
that's actually a really nice thing to
do
I've been trying to work towards that so
as my wife for about five years and
we're still not able to have a Sabbath
day that's but the goal is to try to
reach that this this summer you know the
no electronics almost necessary is
actually a great idea because it's so
easy to get sucked in to the world of
social media the world of Google Amazon
Facebook all these things are designed
to entice us to spend more and more time
there we know this you know that it's
part of what they call an attention
economy they're trying to suck up as
much as possible we need to take back as
much as we can I do want to get to the
two Titas question about introverts you
know as are things different for them so
Tito do you want to unmute Andry ask the
question no okay well I I mean I think
that we can talk about differences
between like extroverts way at the
extrovert end where they need and crave
that human interaction and then like
really you know the most introverted of
the interpreters and everything in
between like my wife for example is an
introvert who likes to have you know
doing public speaking to the large
groups also enjoys you know one-on-one
meetings but winds up having to do a lot
of the in between meetings and a drain
sir
I a myself you know when I teach a class
I have that that kind of like oh
afterwards if you feel a little bit like
you've run a marathon or something
because I put a lot of what I do it's
like almost like actors for a performing
on stage you know I'm making Plato speak
or something like that but but I'm not
an introvert I actually you know I I
seek out those sorts of things and I
notice there's that there's a difference
there and how we handle the
inside my wife is quite frankly
perfectly happy with quarantine oh it
actually removes some obligations to be
engaged with people and face-to-face
settings that that she is happy about
you know and and you know we have also
discovered that there are many meetings
that could be an email she's she's happy
with that with me and I actually miss
being in the classroom with my students
the most in part because I and like you
know I like the kids that I have and I
enjoy engaging with them but it's not
it's not something that's really like
it's not driving me crazy or anything I
think there are some people who are
probably really needing that kind of
human stimulation like they'd like to be
going to sports events and now you know
we can't be there all together and
that's really wearing on them and you
know there is a there is a legitimate
place for that sort of stuff in life
Tania has a comment here building on
mark mark sharing about waking up and
thinking about past experiences I find
an interesting connection between the
going to the liminal space is upon
waking and going to sleep reminding my
unconscious yeah I think that that's
completely right and and like you know I
mentioned daydreaming in the middle of
the day when you just let your mind
wander I think that's another way to
access that as well and sometimes it can
be object focus like you know you're
looking outside and watching the birds
flying around and you're not you're not
watching them because you're going to do
anything with that you're just sort of
like letting your mind pick up on
particular objects I think that's part
of what Rilke suggests viewing and
that's that's part of what Epictetus or
Aristotle would say is being able to be
by yourself and just enjoy yourself you
know Peter I know you wanted to you had
some things that you wanted to talk
about yeah this was a little bit of a
haphazard Homan session today with the
question-and-answer and we only have
seven minutes so maybe I'll close with a
question for you
sure and yeah maybe it's a statement on
maybe I can tease a question out of this
but what's coming up is Zach Stein was
at the stove a couple weeks ago and he
was talking about how this is an
opportunity to be in right relationship
with being at home it's similar what
you're talking about and how sort of
like in these uh slates play
capitalistic stages how we almost
instrumentalize the home it's like yeah
the home like we used a home as a place
to like eat and sleep to go to work
to be productive and build these kind of
fragile castles right and then now we're
forced at home and now this is an
opportunity to build the relationship
with it and what's coming up is this
another environmentalist or some some of
them calling rewilding like rewilding
things and it's almost like the term
rehoming like we gotta every home things
so I don't I don't know if I have a
question there but just anything came
alive or not when I said that I think it
is it is a big shift for for a lot of
people and actually this ties in well
with with a question that can kind of
deepen this from actually a Pathak major
restriction on solitude is domestic
abuse child abuse conditions out here in
India get worse when there's a pandemic
and redressal mechanism that aren't
essential services do I think the
celebration of solitude is a first-world
phenomenon I would say definitely not I
mean it's it's found in almost every
spiritual path or tradition going way
back into ancient times and this is a
major problem here in Milwaukee where we
live you know all these kids being home
we know that child abuse has has spiked
and same thing with domestic abuse we
have some of the poorest ZIP codes in
the United States in this city so you
know what I mean what I'm suggesting
here isn't something that's meant to
address that I mean when it comes to to
any sort of like personal development or
spiritual path there's a lot of
different components to it this
component is not meant to
try to address that that said having had
quite a few students who have dealt with
these sorts of issues and having had a
lot of family members sometimes those
those experiences which are very
negative and shouldn't happen can also
be part of what gets gets used and
transformed within with it that solitude
as well so yeah so we have about four
minutes so I think it's prudent to close
here do you have any closing thoughts
for anyone on the subject or things you
can direct them to to read more about it
well so there's a few questions here
about like well with what medieval
authors and and mark is right the Desert
Fathers who you know would include say
John Cassian and Evagrius Ponte cos you
know the whole monastic tradition is is
worth checking out in part because they
made developing an interior life as part
of the structured life depending on what
order they were in honest Terry central
to what they were doing and you know so
like I mentioned st. Anselm I was at
Benedict and his prose alone is quite an
interesting book for looking at going
going within there's a lot of other
medieval authors who spend time on that
and it became more and more of a thing
as we get into late the late medieval
period you know leading into what we
notice set the cutoff at the Renaissance
but I mean you can also think about like
what Descartes is doing is activity
within solitude right this this
meditative process that he's doing which
is not just a purely abstract thing and
so there's there's like countless
authors over over the ages in ancient
times you know Epictetus has an entire
chapter in the discourses in book three
it's chapter 13 where he talks about
that Aristotle I mentioned we're looking
at nickim akane ethics books eight and
nine
Marcus you know the inner Citadel I
don't remember the exact reference point
for that maybe damn can can provide that
but there's there's a lot of discussions
about this throughout ancient very
ethics and then running through the
dozens your father's early monastic
literature and all the way down to the
present and I would you know I would say
whoever helps you in this use that it's
it's not as if we have to have a canon
of people that we you know we have to
all stick to or something like that
cool cool and people can find you on
your YouTube channel that's for you
update most these days you would say
well in terms of updates Twitter or my
Facebook page are probably the best
places to look but if they they're
interested in videos yeah the YouTube
channel I'm putting out about a video a
day and I also the Sadler's lectures
podcast as well and let me put in a plug
too for I have a friend here in
Milwaukee who's also the co-leader of
the the stoic fellowship and we have
been doing a radio show called wisdom
from life which will be airing later on
today episode five will be airing at
four o'clock central time so five
o'clock Eastern Time cool is that with
Nick no my friend Dan Hays okay cool
yeah awesome well thanks so much for
coming on then sure yeah second time at
the store I will send you the video
afterwards so some closing thoughts or
announcements we got two events coming
up this evening one called the metagame
mastermind and it's just sort of like
having mastermind groups keep each other
accountable to kind of these things that
really shamed on Twitter for not doing
together and then later we have a Tyson
we have something about freestyle during
a pandemic or freestyling during a
pandemic in Tyson's here do you want to
give it a quick plug Tyson yeah we will
be deepening our relationship with unser
t-through freestyle rap so I'd love to
flow with you all there I'm nervous and
excited for that one
um lastly the the Stowe is based off a
gift economy viewing it as a gift for us
to use during this time of need if
there's any inspiration demonic
inspiration to provide a gift to the
stoah you just go to the stolid CA /
gift I will put it on the website right
now or on the chat for more information
alright everyone thanks so much for
coming on thanks great thanks great
welcome